hi so before we start I just wanted to
give you an update
Geshe Michaels fine we've we think that
the antibiotic that he's been taking is
not really working and so we he feels
and sera nee who's been taking care of
him feels they better go and check it
out and they're taking him to the doctor
right now
there may be a gall bladder infection
which has been an ongoing minor issue so
but believe me everything is fine and I
think you need to rest assure that I
strongly the other day that it was such
a crashing moment of impermanence you
know that we have to get ready all of us
it's not just about it's about us we
have to get ready and I think that was
maybe truly one of the beautiful lessons
for me that he was teaching us and for
me especially but what would be the
antidote for us and I think we could
just take a short meditation five-minute
meditation on I think we joy sing about
Geshe Michaels extraordinary way of
bringing these these beautiful teachings
into the world and not holding it in a
sanctimonious academic session of a few
people he's given us clear insight and
and really deep understanding with
examples of the pen and and the two
husbands and think about all the
extraordinary gifts he gave us this week
the last ten days it's remarkable what
what we can take home and rejoice about
but I think if we took a few minutes and
just rejoiced about the last 10 days
here and think about what he gave you
personally
just just tune into what you feel you
can take home in your minds and hearts
and and and and rejoice in that because
you are not the same human being that
you walked onto this land 10 days ago
okay you are not and you will know that
maybe in a little bit more of a distant
of time from here but I think it would
be a gift to him so just take that
minute to a few minutes and give him and
give all of us together this gift that
we're learning truly the deep deep
universal principles that function and
that can be changed we can see our lives
improving and we can see our world and
proofing and wish him good health at the
end send him your beautiful seeds for
health so let's just take a few minutes
I think it would be a gift that we can
always you know give our practice it's a
strong powerful gift
okay so we're at the final SEI class
it's called correct view and actually I
where I quickly read through my notes
and Connie's notes that we've taken and
geshe-la really spoke on all the points
already
so I'll just reinforce of the class but
we covered many of the points that this
class does cover and there's only two
homework questions it's pretty cool
you're off you're off the hook
two homework questions you could do that
before you get on the bus or on the bus
okay and so in the process of the
correct view what is correct view mark
mark mark did it he just had to do this
we we we know go ahead yeah
the see things I mean actually the
principle is to see that things are
coming from you Oh everything ultimately
the good bad the so-called unfair and
the most beautiful things are all coming
from you and we understand this idea
correct of the two realities we we know
the pen we know the whole story of the
pen is really expressing the
simultaneous realities in the same space
right so when when we teach in DCI or
when you teach an ACI the pen you get to
this place right where the puppy comes
into the room and they take the pen and
they chew on it and that moment we say
in DCI language who's right is the pen a
pen or is it a chew toy and usually
people get it and say well both are
right there are two realities coexisting
in the same space but they're more than
two realities coexisting in the same
space but the example of the pen and the
chew toy is really a beautiful metaphor
to understand that simultaneously these
two levels of reality are coexisting all
the time all the time what about other
realms you know we know these realms
exist we have to kind of maybe trust the
the scripture right we you know I I
remember people in three retreat coming
to me and saying you know I went to the
forum realm oh my god it was incredible
like ice my mind was in the form around
for a while it was really cool
but unless you have a valid perception
of that it has to be taken what for
you know okay well we believe that the
Scriptures are saying there are other
realms that are coexisting
simultaneously even the state of Nirvana
even the state of Nirvana would be any
of you who could be under cover our
hearts would be directly experiencing
the rule the whole room and the
environment and all the beings in this
room in a completely different
perceptual reality it's not somewhere
else in other words it's here in this
very space simultaneously we just don't
have the seeds to actually experience it
possibly maybe you do I'm just speaking
of myself and so these two truths are we
you know are we in a sense stuck in the
conventional truths or what we labeled
the other day as deceptive truth we're
being forced pretty much on a daily
basis to experience the world this way
pretty much I mean you know you have you
have intellectual perceptions of this
right I mean the whole point of what
we're teaching about emptiness is to
intellectually on our highest level and
and and any of the schools levels to get
those seeds to be proactively reminding
ourselves that were stuck in this
reality we have to continue to remind
ourselves during every of event during a
so-called normal day that the world is
totally not doing this it's coming this
way and when we study emptiness and in
the Buddhist systems
one thing Geshe Michael reminded us that
the more we hear this pen the more we
understand in meditation when we analyze
emptiness the more we study the quality
of those seeds prevents us from what yes
going to the lower realms not taking a
rebirth in a lower realm and that's a
remarkable gift if we really get our
hands and our heads around reality and
the pen and understand these ultimate
two realities ultimate and conventional
or deceptive reality constantly working
in our mind you know we're doing we're
doing this more than this but if we're
doing we're on the right track you see
and that's where the laboratory of life
kicks in and we begin the practice of
remembering emptiness in our so-called
normal daily routines with family and
business associates and traffic jams and
you know constipation all of the above
we have to remember this right and it
slips the mind maybe three to five
thousand times a day I'm not sure but
there is this possibility right that we
can really it's almost as if like
sometimes we have to do this like you
know you know it's like it's it's just
like going to the Hilton gym right
you're like okay I will restrain myself
I won't let that emotion overcharge me
and the charge is essentially always
neutralizing if it's negative we're
trying to understand not to have the
overwhelming emotion that's charging the
perception of this
take us over so we do this and then
create more suffering in our future and
so if we could really understand the pen
and we're going to talk about the
conditions and the seeds that we have to
plant in order to actually have a direct
perception of the pen in this class
which a couple of you asked me about
today then we have some really
foundational launchpad to go into our
world every day with a very precise map
of how to handle ourselves you know in
the I call them the mining fields of a
given day you know I became a news
junkie recently it's crazy there's a
radio station called an NPR which is
somewhat unbiased but I I suddenly when
I'm not having my hit of news you know
like when I'm not listening to any given
day in the White House I get kind of
like I don't know like I need to hear
the the latest buzz on what's going on
in the Trump world and then I I mean I I
do I realize that it's just pure it's
pure almost gossip right it's almost
like I call it now the ultimate reality
show that it's actually a reality show
that I'm actually looking for I want the
entertainment of it as opposed to the
shocking value of what is going on
inside our country and I love the
entertainment of it and it you know
that's kind of a I I fooled myself into
thinking that I need to know about
what's truly going on conventionally in
our country by actually getting
entertained by
the the sound bites that are very
dramatic and very shockingly emotional
eat in a tangible you get excited or
something pulls you in a certain
direction and you know maybe my test
today will be when I'm starting to drive
to Phoenix I don't turn the radio on you
know and maybe we'll listen to gives you
Michaels you know teaching on emptiness
from you know DC i7 you know if that's
my struggle is how do I flip that over
you know I mean how many times could I
hear about the Mueller report on the you
know on the fixing of an election in
then I like take that habit and then
just okay let's listen to DC I 7h
Hedrick and really get another spin on
how to understand what gives you Michael
is teaching us so that's my struggle you
know not wasting a single minute of time
on the crap that's invading our minds on
any given stimulating moment even at the
gas pump you're getting stimulated by
some video to get a free car wash you
know if you you know get for refills on
your gas tank
there's stimulation that just takes us
into this world all the time the whole
process is this it's to keep you here
it's to stay in the deceptive reality
and diamond mountain is kind of
beautiful but Connie and I believe that
it could be a mixed blessing to have
internet in your cabin we feel that it
it you know that the seduction is there
to go online and watch something that is
not relevant to what your retreat is all
about and if we did a retreat with it
we'd totally turn it off
so when you know when you see the direct
perception of emptiness for 20 minutes
everything you've done up to the point
of seeing emptiness has contributed to
that direct perception all the countless
hours of classroom study all the
homeworks and quizzes and final
examinations all the meditation hours
that you've put in all of these are
contributing in in subtle and not so
subtle ways to your ultimate direct
experience of a 20 minute higher reality
and we don't see that when we're in the
trench of doing the work we're not
actually I'm not like keeping an
accounting book on how many hours I do
of meditation a week or a month or how
many hours I've spent teaching or how
many hours I've spent listening the
accumulation is subtle them are not
listening to or experiencing I don't I'm
personally saying this we're not
experiencing radical change in our
practice but in in another personal
experience and we we kind of call this
like throwing karma things can ripen so
quickly like and we say certain parts of
your life do that getting married having
a child being born getting a divorce
having a tragic accident getting the
best job of your life those those
Karma's that accumulate and suddenly
come out of nowhere
is is something that I think you have to
expect on one level in your practice and
the honesty of a good meditation
practice really is five days of just
struggle and then maybe on the sixth day
you have like four incredible just
inexplicably beautiful minutes you see
you know just you've done the struggling
and the the effort of staying
the cushion and staying on the object
for if you've done a 50 minute
meditation you've you've stayed on the
object for eight minutes or 12 minutes
and it was hard and then the day you
least expect it when you don't want to
sit and you sit on the cushion you get
these Eureka moments these four minutes
these three minutes where something is
opening up in your heart and you see
something that is so exquisitely
beautiful it may not be the direct
perception but it could be a depth of
understanding the direct perception or
dependent origination and that's where
the hard work comes in but when you get
those tastes it is the ultimate carrot
you know it is this thing that just
teases you along to say oh my god it's
worth the seven hours this week to get
those four and a half minutes it's just
like unbelievably sweet thank you I'll
do another eight hours next week and we
have to remember it balances out
eventually where you can go deeper
quicker but in my my my life with
meditation it still consists of a good
20 minutes of grunt work before I can
drop into a place where I feel that the
the subtle mind and body become aware
again it's still to this day takes me
that long and it's just a reality check
for those of you who are obsessively
wanting to have the direct perception no
less than one hour a day no less than
six days a week honestly that's the way
it is the 15 minute you know cookie
class DCI idea it's just to hook people
in but but by DC i7 it's like okay
you're grown up you've been given
financial freedom you've been given
teachings on health and relationships
and inner peace now this is what you
need to do it's an hour or more a day
and that doesn't include your yoga yoga
is the perfect complement to your
meditation and we you know that's it's
so true our esoteric systems like tai
chi or chi Kong are Aikido where you're
really moving Chi and you're really
feeling the energy transference through
the subtle mind and body it is essential
I think to meditation for fast-tracking
meditation and so that's kind of the
reality of of wanting to see emptiness
are one of the components that
contribute to seeing it but if you have
the indirect perception of a higher
level of reality the understanding of
the higher schools of men of emptiness
it's you're on the path you are on the
path and a lot of people are kind of
tuning in to the six flavors of
emptiness that we begin the classes with
earlier with Geshe Michael it's a
beautiful entry into the stream of
emptiness to get the flavors of
emptiness from the different schools and
you know listen to that that that
teaching there's there's I think there's
one main AC I practice listed under
practices that happened in 1998 in
California I was there and it's online
listen to it
it's a beautiful introduction to re I
say to remind us of the different
schools and the flavors because each of
us are doing those flavors all the time
we're all not at 5 or 4 or 6 we're doing
one and then we're doing five and we're
doing three but we're doing it you see
where we're using our perception of the
logic of understanding emptiness to go
higher and deeper
and then go on the cushion you see don't
leave it intellectually go deeper and
analyze it for you and the class just
now about me and mine incredibly
beautiful opportunity to start doing a
meditation on me and mine go looking for
them me go looking for the mine you know
spend 40 minutes like searching it where
is it
deductive Lee come back to the place of
where it's not go backward like you know
am i my fingers am i my toes am i my
eyes am i my consciousness where is me
where is mine that's a great meditation
on emptiness and give yourself patience
with it it can take you into deeper
parts of the you know of the equation of
single-pointed concentration
what's the other side of the coin from
emptiness what's the the flip side of
the same coin
yeah interdependence or dependent
origination
we have to learn karma and the
realizations of karma are are also
equivalent to the full the full package
to gain a higher understanding of
emptiness but also to actually have the
direct perception of emptiness and we're
gonna do something later how many of you
have not heard the two husbands in the
kitchen one oh my god you all have okay
I think we should still do it
you should still do it yeah
not yet not yet but I'll get ready in a
minute but when I heard it in Singapore
when I came out of retreat I thought it
was a stroke of genius it was just oh my
god this is remarkable it just put
everything into perspective for me we
were also in a teaching in Beijing at
the China at the Beijing opera house
there were 2,800 people in the audience
and on the stage were two Buddhist
scholars from University of Beijing do
you remember that Stanley it was just
incredible - one of them was like this
renowned scholar who had written books
you know like 28 books on Buddhism and
he got up onto the roster and it was
just pain he spoke for like an hour
and you were trying to Stanley was
trying to translate you know and and it
was just I it was so abstract and obtuse
that I couldn't get my head around any
of it and then Geshe Michael got up and
taught the two husbands in the kitchen
to an audience of 2,800 people to teach
dependent origination and I just
remember the faces of these two scholars
they were like you know like what the
hell is he talking about and it was so
beautiful it was a moment where I think
the audience kind of like got relaxed
and started kind of clapping
it was just a beautiful lesson to
understand that there's so many ways to
you know trends transmitted dependent
origination and emptiness and I'm not
saying one is valid and the other isn't
but it was certainly a confirmation that
people understood the two husbands and
the reality of its complexity about
emptiness the gotcha dependent
origination karma it's all in the
kitchen and that to me is worth doing at
least a hundred and fifty two hundred
times so I've gotten in the mode of
doing it and we're gonna do it in a
minute okay the good news is yet all of
us in the room have the opportunity to
have the direct perception the good news
also is that you have to have an
incredible banking of good seeds to see
it directly I mean it's just amazing I
you know I you have to have merit merit
merit it's like you have to have the 1k
membership for United Airlines something
like that you you like all the time you
have to have 1k where they pick you up
when you get off the plane to take you
by car to your next plane or something
you have to have that kind of karma to
see it but I think you're in the room so
the karmic seeds are there can a Buddha
see emptiness directly at the same time
as omniscient mind right they can see
emptiness directly they're perceiving
emptiness directly every moment
simultaneously while they're being
omniscient you know let's let's go out
and have fun and let's see who needs us
in Phoenix on Easter Sunday some kid is
crying because the Easter egg that they
got and chocolate wasn't their favorite
flavor all right let's do something
about it let's send her nomination
to them or oh my god you know there's so
many people having dinner alone let's
see let's send them some visitors maybe
they can have a nice Easter so the idea
of omniscience is such a cool idea that
the other two bodies of the Buddha you
know their mnemonic ayah the body of the
Buddha that can emanate in any place
time or planet is is constantly sending
out perfect karmic correlations to you
to help you out in forms that are I
don't know heavy winds at Diamond
Mountain or you know I don't know
cute little javelinas that you know come
around to your cabin or the other day
there was beautiful rain at 4:00 a.m. in
the morning I thought it was gorgeous
the moon coming up here the other day
was just spectacular those are the nice
things they come in nasty packages too
right there's not you know the
equanimity of karma is you know Buddha's
can appear and give you really tragic
so-called appearing tragic things happen
divorces or you know people say you know
after five years after my divorce god my
husband was so wise like it wasn't for
him I would have never met my perfect
partner people say that to us you know
like it's incredible you know I hated
that guy or that girl I hate you know we
just hated each other and but at the
same time he knew I had to move on she
knew I had to move on so it's not like
in pretty packages all the time
the tough stuff has to happen too and
holding this view is so crucial in those
moments that the true trials where you
are being tested in on those levels are
essential to
ripening and purifying enormous seeds in
order to launch you to a higher
understanding and to a happier life
actually so we said you know an hour a
day is really including the
preliminaries you know we did some
beautiful preliminary practices here and
[Music]
you know those can be considered
warm-ups but they're also very powerful
seed planting objects you bring a
teacher in front of you and you do the
preliminaries every day you're fast
tracking your practice we have to be
serving other people that's number two
and this is uh this goes with meditation
this is like the another aspect of your
meditation how do you serve and what do
you how do you find that you know that
perfect place to serve well Diamond
Mountain is a great place
i I always think of karmic objects being
on certain levels to serve and I don't
know in my early days I used to serve my
company got behind an organization that
goes to shut-ins or lonely people who
can't cook for themselves so every
Friday we would go and serve meals to
them bring them meals to their house and
usually clean up their kitchen or you
know help them kind of clean up their
house and it was really beautiful you
saw the the sadness of lonely people
living alone in small little apartments
in New York City you know it's just
surviving on a thread literally because
they're not having support from family
and not being fed or properly you know
hygienic ly taken care of because
there's no money for them and so that
was always a beautiful thing for me to
do when I was working full-time I didn't
have time to do much more but I think it
served
beautifully and it opens you up to
understanding the suffering firsthand
but most of you have that already in
your your bag you have service you have
it's almost like you're you could teach
service all of you because that's who
you are it's innate in your your you
know your process you know you need to
serve bees no matter what form it takes
you you need it it's like you know it's
it's just essential for life you're
creating beautiful seeds for being alive
by taking care of others constantly oh
no by the way you're you're building
seeds for health both mental and
physical health but serving is cool and
guess you Michael just saved my butt you
know I I was a guy living in New York
he saved my butt and I I wasn't really
looking for him
like Maria said I you know I could care
less about teaching Buddhism before I
met Peter but it was this thing right
where I was living a pretty cool life I
was you know pretty cool life I had you
know a penthouse apartment and a BMW and
a great job and I was flying around the
world and I had you know a really cool
partner and and you know all these kind
of seductive things came into my life
you know I never had to take the subway
I just take taxis and you know time oh
okay 15 please okay anyway long story
short I wasn't happy and when I bumped
into Geshe Michael he sort of knew that
I knew it but I didn't want to admit it
and he
he he did basically reflect that deeply
in my heart that it was really something
really was missing in my life and my own
suffering was in denial and two years
later radically happened I quit my job
and took over ACIP which is for me a
karmic object that is so essentially
important to the world and to him and to
our organization in general and so I was
fortunate enough to have that cusp of
karma ripen and then radically shift my
life within 18 months everything changed
the whole paradigm of my my life changed
completely and I never looked back and
and I was grateful for that process and
all of you are plugging in like that on
projects throughout the world and please
don't stop it just dedicate the hell out
of it just work it for all it's worth
work it three jewels this man this man
and his partner have basically made the
three jewels of New York honestly one of
the most beautiful pristine successful
struggling but paying bill bayit bills
Center in New York City it's incredible
what's going on in that that place and
it's magical to go back to New York and
have a three jewels that is functioning
for hundreds of people who go and take
meditation training and yoga training
and ACI teachings and Steven like my god
thank you you know amazing
so maybe in three years you guys won't
be teaching there honestly you could you
could probably do a gig at the three
jewels and your ACR careers in your
future okay
study study study you've got to keep
studying that's number four
let's do the two husbands so we're going
to teach you two husbands and talk about
dependent origination the gotcha
emptiness karmic correlations and we'll
do it quickly Peter maybe not Seiji
hoo-yeah Maria come
so Jenny's my kid Lucas my kid
okay we set it up this way I'm a working
mom I'm a liberated new woman of the
21st century you know birth control
didn't work for me in any event you know
being liberated woman means pretty much
basically my husband stays at home most
of the time he makes a little money but
essentially I take care of the kids I
bring home the financial support to pay
the bills and I cook I mean it's a full
20-hour day and so that's my life but
I'm happy and I'm exhausted
and the sin of today is that my boss
called me in today and she said be ready
tomorrow at 6:30 in the morning come to
the office you better not be late
because we have an important meeting
with a new client who's based in Los
Angeles I'm in Guangzhou I said okay
I'll be there like a brand new client
could change the business for the fiscal
year to 20 so what do I do well first I
got to get the kids ready so I'm gonna
go to the kids room they're back from
school hi kids how are you you're good
how was school yeah how's your grades
today did you did you have a test
okay listen mommy's got an important
meeting tomorrow I want you to listen
put everything away
take that laptop away so mommy is got to
be at the office at 6:30 you need to be
dressed and ready for school by 6:00
a.m. I'm gonna set the alarm in your
room I'm gonna come into your room and
you promise to be ready you promise your
homeworks gonna be done all right good
all right
okay so you know I make husband you know
I make the husband happy that night you
know and even I made him dinner you know
everything's cool on that side you know
I wake up at 6:00 and 5:30 and I go into
the kids rooms hi kids
are you ready they're having a pillow
fight kids what are you doing what are
you doing I told you yesterday what did
I tell you you were supposed to be ready
with your clothes on and your homework
and you're a mess get dressed you are
the two stupidest kids in Guangzhou ah
my god what do I do I get to work we cut
the deal the client loved it he loved
the presentation I made I'm like really
happy about that
I'm exhausted I go I thought you know
I'll make some nice dinner for my
husband or my family I go to this store
I'm gonna make some sushi from scratch
and maybe some a'my tofu and we'll have
a beautiful dinner and I just want to
spend some time with him and I just want
a hug I I just I'm so tired and I just
want him to hold me so I'd go shopping
and I drag my stuff in and I'm pretty
much ready to open the door and I'm just
thinking you know I can't wait to see
him you know he's been so good up till
now and I just want a hug hi honey how
are you how you doing what what did you
say
I'm stupid
I didn't do anything he's calling me
stupid I just went shopping to buy this
whole beautiful dinner I was coming in
and just wanting a hug ah it's not my
fault I didn't do anything I just simply
wanted a beautiful night with my husband
and my kids
why did that happen what was the point
they came out of nowhere he came out of
nowhere
why why do you why won't you do that to
me honey
ah it's not my fault so what just
happened three main things happened why
do why is there a second husband in the
kitchen which husband came from my sees
this one or this one
yeah Maria is came well she's my real
husband I planted that husband what
about this husband which husband is this
it's not my fault husband it's not my
fault my god husband number two not my
fault
but how did that not my fault husband
get into the kitchen well no that's how
my real husband got into the kitchen I
yelled at the kids last week because
they were screwing around not being
ready
I told I called them stupid hi honey
you see so yeah I planted the seed for
this husband husband number one the
blonde to actually you know have the
moment of what resulting right dependent
origination come back to me but what
about this husband number number 2
husband say what yeah this has been
coming this way it's not my fault could
never exist without me planting this
husband okay five minutes I get you so
what is that called well there's a word
called the cha sake gotcha as I'm
sure it's one of your 21 were it words
right yeah so the gotcha is the thing
that emptiness is empty of remember that
the thing that emptiness is empty of the
gotcha the second husband could never
exist has never existed and will never
exist you see but we put that husband
there because why yeah because we're
hardwired we're born as Geshe Michael so
today just have the world coming this
way and that's really profound
and that happens too today tomorrow and
as many times as our lives exist if we
don't see the direct perception of
emptiness we're hardwired that way but
thank you husbands thank you kids okay I
have five minutes so to wrap it up
that's dependent origination
that's emptiness that's the gotcha let's
see if we're finished with the class I
think that's enough
Tim Tim needs to keep me on time
questions anyone
yes
I really like how during the luxury you
said deceptive reality for some somehow
this term really kind of struck me and I
was thinking what could be the seeds for
us to see this reality as deceptive like
what are the subtle things that we do to
keep this ignorance going yeah if we
could call it all pervasive ignorance
beginning as lifetime's of
misunderstanding the pen essentially you
have to remember we we always come in
with the seeds from our past right the
constant countless seeds that are being
pushed into your next life with you so
we're we're in this circle when we're
born automatically we're already in this
this circle unless you've been unless
you have attained an extraordinary past
life of an are hot where you could
potentially rebirth by your decision to
help other beings you see but other than
that all of us are still having the
world this way coming being forced by
beginning us lifetimes you know in a
short precise way that's that's the
answer but you're here you see you've
done some serious work in the past and
you've gotten seeds to be in this room
talking about these profound ideas so
something is up and you've got to trust
it fully to know that you have seeds
from your past that also is trying to
understand the ultimate nature of all
things and that's cool that's all you
need to know really okay
I guess we'll do the prayer just one
word
[Music]
some guessing do
make
[Music]
Q partial eat I'm good right now Mandela
Camacho
a tsunami a share so social nature
Tom Paco Nieto farsh okay thank you so
much
[Applause]